Inventory of the Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (I) 1780-1929
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Group D: Brown and Tucker Papers, 1839-1929., 5 boxes. (Box-folder 20-24)
  - Letters to Henry Peronneau Brown, oldest son of the Hon. John Thompson Brown, written by his widowed mother, Mrs. Mary E. Brown, of Petersburg; family correspondence after his marriage to Frances Bland Coalter (see also Box 6) in the Civil War and Reconstruction years; twelve letters from John C
    - Receipt for 65 pounds of ice to Henry Peronneau Brown from Long and Stevens, Petersburg, 11 July 1857. (Box-folder 21:5)
    - F[anny] B. Coalter to Henry Peronneau Brown, May-July 1858., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:6)
      Affectionate letters to her fiance.
    - Mrs. B[etty] C. Lacy, Chatham, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, at the New York Hotel, 23 December 1858. (Box-folder 21:7)
    - Henry T. Coalter, Hanover, to his sister Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 24 December 1858. (Box-folder 21:8)
    - Mrs. Betty C. Lacy and Margaret Barnes, Chatham, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 11 January 1859. (Box-folder 21:9)
    - Hess to Mrs. Brown, at Oak Springs, 8 February 1859. (Box-folder 21:10)
    - Carrie, Otter [Hills], to "Dear Cousin," n.d. (Box-folder 21:11)
    - Mrs. Betty C. Lacy, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, March-November 1859., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:12)
      In August she writes to console Mrs. Brown on the death of her mother, Mrs. Judith H. Coalter.
    - Lucy T. Braxton to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown at Loving Creek P.O., March-December 1859., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:13)
      "We are all as glad, dear Fanny, that your home is so lovely and you are so happy...for its mountain scenery."
    - John Coalter II, to his sister Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, March-September 1859., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:14)
      Concerning the failing health of their mother.
    - Cousin Sue, Vaucluse, to Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 8 August 1859. (Box-folder 21:15)
      Consolations on the death of Mrs. Coalter.
    - Mrs. T. Magill, Winchester, to Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], August-November 1859., 2 letters. ALS. Covers lacking. (Box-folder 21:16)
    - C. B. T. Washington, Williamsburg, to Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 9 September 1859., ALS. Cover lacking. (Box-folder 21:17)
    - Mrs. B[etty] B. Dallam, Baltimore, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 31 September 1859. (Box-folder 21:18)
    - Mrs. Mary W. Braxton, Chericoke, to Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 17 November 1859. (Box-folder 21:19)
      Concerning the loss of an infant.
    - St. George Tucker Coalter, University of Virginia, to his sister Mrs. Fanny Bland [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown] Brown, 9 December 1859. (Box-folder 21:20)
    - L. T. Moore to Mr. and Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, n.d., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:21)
    - M. E. Irvine, Buffalo, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, n.d. (Box-folder 21:22)
    - Mrs. Betty B. Dallam, Baltimore, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 11 January 1860. (Box-folder 21:23)
    - Cousin Sue, Richmond, to Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 6 March 1860. (Box-folder 21:24)
    - Mrs. Eliza P. Willers, Fleur de Hundred, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, March-May 1860., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:25)
    - Mrs. V. C. Braxton to Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 7 March 1860. (Box-folder 21:26)
    - Mrs. Betty C. Lacy, Chatham, to Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 9 March 1860. (Box-folder 21:27)
    - Eight calling cards in a cover addressed to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 10 March 1860., 8 items. ALS. (Box-folder 21:28)
    - John Coalter II, Moon's Mount, to his sister Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 19 March 1860. (Box-folder 21:29)
      The bachelor brother of Mrs. Brown writes that his loneliness on an out-of-the-way plantation is heading him to the madhouse.
    - F[anny] T. Bryan, Eagle Point, to her cousin, Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 28 May 1860. (Box-folder 21:30)
    - [Rev.] Moses D. Hoge, Prince Edward, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 31 July 1860. (Box-folder 21:31)
    - Mrs. M[ary] G. Braxton, Ingleside, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, May-July 1861., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:32)
      She writes of the ladies making vests and shirts for the soldiers. News that the Yankees have landed at Hampton; the first of the war casualties in the family.
    - Mrs. G[inny] B. Grinnan to her cousin, Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 17 May 1861. (Box-folder 21:33)
      Making clothes for the army: "1500 yards have just been received which we are to turn our attention to at once."
    - John Coalter II, Moon's Mount, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 29 May 1861. (Box-folder 21:34)
      His house was set afire and cannon are firing all about. Comments on "the tennessee company...the roughest men you ever saw..."
    - Mrs. Margaret T. Martin, West Brook, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 28 July 1861. (Box-folder 21:35)
    - Mrs. Mary S. Brown, Williamsburg, to Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 3 August 1861. (Box-folder 21:36)
      The wife of John Thompson Brown II, is in "this antiquated spot" because her husband was drilling some new troops and sent for her to join him.
    - A "Comic Valentine," from Stanley, the family home, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 7 August 1861. (Box-folder 21:37)
    - St. George Tucker Coalter to his sister [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 30 August 1861. (Box-folder 21:38)
      Their brother, Henry, is at a camp near Williamsburg; the other brother, John, is in Richmond.
    - M. A. Tomlin, Clifton, to Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 28 September 1861. (Box-folder 21:39)
    - Mrs. F. C. Young, Westbrook, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 15 November 1861., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:40)
    - Agreement of a sale of land between Thos. Burroughs and K. G. Holland, 25 October 1862. (Box-folder 21:41)
      "adjoining the lands of Henry Peronneau Brown and others."
    - J. R. Bryan, Cargobrook, to John [Coalter II], 11 May 1864. (Box-folder 21:42)
      "I am sorry Henry's name is not in the list of exchanged prisoners..."
    - Deed for transfer of land from Thos. Burroughs to K. G. Holland, 3 September 1864. (Box-folder 21:43)
    - Henry T. Coalter, prisoner at Fort Pulaski, Georgia, to his sister, Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, November-December 1864., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:44)
    - Receipt for wheat delivered by Bassett's Farm, King William Couny, signed A. Wynne and L. Hatchet, 1868. (Box-folder 21:45)
    - George Bagby, Tappahannock, to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, 3 February 1869. (Box-folder 21:46)
      Request for someone to serve the Presbyterian Church at Tappahannock.
    - John Coalter, witness to sale at G. W. Bassett's estate, 12 February 1869. (Box-folder 21:47)
    - A bill brought in Chancery Court by John R. Bryan against H. B. Tomlin, executor of St. George Tucker Coalter, 14 September 1869. (Box-folder 21:48)
      The settlement of the John Randolph estate which was in litigation for many years.
    - William Phillips, agreement to pay James A. Lipscomb, 30 October 1869. (Box-folder 21:49)
    - Rev. John G. Shepperson, Bedford, to Mrs. F. B. Brown and to Mrs. John Thompson Brown, 8 February 1870. (Box-folder 21:50)
    - H. B. Tomlin, Brandywine (formerly Old Church) to John Coalter II, 15 March 1870. (Box-folder 21:51)
      Refuses a request for $500 by his nephew; recommends that he stop drinking.
    - Receipt by Everett Twann, Curie's Neck, to John Coalter II, for wages, 9 May 1871. (Box-folder 21:52)
    - Bills of Mrs. Peronneau Brown, 1872-1873., 2 items. PDS. (Box-folder 21:53)
    - Accounts of John Coalter II, with stores, 1873-1874., 3 items. PDS. (Box-folder 21:54)
    - J[ohn] T[hompson] Brown III, Evington, Virginia, to his mother, Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 9 July 1875. (Box-folder 21:55)
      Note written on an early "penny post card."
    - John Coalter II, Walnut Hill, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, February-December 1878., 12 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:56)
      Letters written to his sister as he made a start in farming after the end of the war: "I have not the means to buy me a suit of clothes." Later he added: "I never was as poor in my life before as I am now...I have not spent during the whole year on myself more than $10..."
    - [?], Stanley, to "My darling little angel," 6 February 1878., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 21:57)
    - Susie Bon to Aunt, n.d. (Box-folder 21:58)
    - Wedding invitation from Mrs. William C. Beale to Mr. and Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 20 August 1878. (Box-folder 21:59)
    - John Coalter II to Fanny, [January 1879]. (Box-folder 21:60)
      First mention of Cassie Tucker, who was later to marry John Thompson Brown III.
    - Lillie Hope Lister, Rockbridge Baths, to Mrs. Brown, 11 November 1880. (Box-folder 21:61)
      A request for a purchase of a case of "56 Home Remedies."
    - Lillie Hope Norton, Charlottesville, Virginia, to Mrs. Brown, 13 April 1881. (Box-folder 21:62)
    - Prints from seed catalogues, Spring 1881., 2 items. (Box-folder 21:63)
    - Store accounts of Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, July-October 1881., 4 items. PDS. (Box-folder 21:64)
    - Mrs. Cynthia Beverly Tucker Coleman, Williamsburg, to Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 1 January 1883. (Box-folder 21:65)
      Writes of Cassie [Tucker], wife of [John] Thompson [Brown III]. "You have introduced into your home a very sunbeam."
    - J. Willcox Brown, Baltimore, to his sister-in-law, Fanny [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 5 February 1883. (Box-folder 21:66)
      Concerning the death of John [Coalter II].
    - Sallie A. Donnan, Petersburg, to "My dear friend," 26 September 1883. (Box-folder 21:67)
    - Seed Catalogues, n.d. (Box-folder 21:68)
    - Statement of H. B. Tomlin concerning the trust for Mrs. Fanny B. Brown [Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown], 10 February 1885. (Box-folder 21:69)
    - Henry Peronneau Brown, Bedford, to Fanny, 13 March 1885. (Box-folder 21:70)
    - Drawing of a house, n.d., 2 items. AD. (Box-folder 21:71)
    Subseries 3: John Thompson Brown III
  - Correspondence of John Thompson Brown III, son of Henry Peronneau Brown, who married Cassie Tucker, thus reuniting the family with the Tucker line. Includes letters of Mrs. Cynthia B. Tucker Coleman, of Williamsburg, 1869-1890., 80 items. (Box 22:1-19)
    The letters in this box concerning John Thompson Brown III, begin with one from his mother, Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, the former Frances Bland Coalter. There are 6 report cards from The University School, Petersburg, Virginia (1877-1879). Of interest is a pamphlet of Resolutions Passed in 1894, 1895, and 1896...Denouncing the Bedford High School Act.
    Many of the letters in the collection are from Mrs. Cynthia B. Tucker Coleman to her niece Cassie (Mrs. John Thompson Brown III). Letters from the children, John Thompson Brown IV, Frances Brown, and Henry Peronneau Brown II, are included as well as photographs of some members of the family and pictures of the family home, Ivy Cliff, Bedford County (formerly Otter Hill) the home of Capt. Henry Brown, great grandfather of John Thompson Brown III.
    At the end of the box is a notebook containing sermons copied out by Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown for her son John Thompson Brown III.
    - Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown to "My Darling Son," 3 May 1869. (Box-folder 22:1)
      To her son [John Thompson Brown III] urging him to improve his writing and "to read your Bible and say your prayers every day."
    - M. M. B. [ ? ], London, England, to [John] Thompson [Brown III], 31 August 1875. (Box-folder 22:2)
      A description of the London Museum and Zoo.
    - Report cards from University School for John Thompson Brown III, some countersigned by Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown, 1877-1879., 6 items. PDS. (Box-folder 22:3)
      Some contain letters by John Thompson Brown III, when the reports were sent home.
    - Paper on Martin Luther written by John Thompson Brown at University School, Petersburg, Virginia, 1879. (Box-folder 22:4)
    - Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown to "My dear boy" [John Thompson Brown III], [1890]. (Box-folder 22:5)
      Recommends Bible reading as the antidote for "the very corrupt sentiments which are scattered through the classical writers."
    - Mrs. Cynthia B. T[ucker] Coleman, Williamsburg, to [John] Thompson [Brown III], September 1894., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 22:6)
      The recent death of her husband, Dr. Coleman; the serious illness of Mrs. Henry Peronneau Brown.
    - Resolutions Passed By Precincts of Bedford County in 1894, 1895, and 1896 Denouncing the Bedford High School Act, 1896. (Box-folder 22:7)
    - Mrs. C[ynthia] B. T[ucker] Coleman, Ivy Cliff, to Cassie [Mrs. John Thompson Brown III], July-August 1898., 8 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 22:8)
      During her illness, Mrs. Brown's children are in the care of Mrs. Coleman.
    - Henry Peronneau Brown II, Ivy Cliff, to "My darling Mama," [Mrs. John Thompson Brown III], 9 August 1898. (Box-folder 22:9)
    - John Thompson Brown III, Brierfield, Bedford County to "My darling wife," August 1898., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 22:10)
    - Elizabeth [Brown] to "My dear Mama" [Mrs. John Thompson Brown III], 14 September 1898. (Box-folder 22:11)
      A child's letter.
    - Mrs. Cynthia [Beverly Tucker Coleman], Williamsburg, to Cassie [Mrs. John Thompson Brown III], 16 October 1898. (Box-folder 22:12)
      Rejoices that Cassie's health is "entirely restored." Bev. Tucker and Braxton Bryan are mentioned as attending an assembly of the clergy at Jamestown.
    - Mrs. Cynthia Beverly Tucker Coleman, Washington City, to Thompson [John Thompson Brown III], January, August 1899., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 22:13)
    - Clipping from The Richmond Dispatch, 31 December 1899. (Box-folder 22:14)
    - Two photographs, one of John Thompson Brown IV and his sister, Frances Bland Coalter Brown, with a servant, Aunt Jane; the other of the house, Ivy Cliff, originally called Otter Hill, [1900]., 2 items. Ph. (Box-folder 22:15)
    - Mrs. Cynthia Beverly Tucker Coleman, Williamsburg, to Cassie [Mrs. John Thompson Brown III], 19 August 1901. (Box-folder 22:16)
    - Mrs. Cynthia Beverly Tucker Coleman, Ivy Cliff and Brampton, to Cassie [Mrs. John Thompson Brown III], September-November 1904., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 22:17)
      "...make haste and get well enough to come home where you are much missed."
    - Bills and business papers of John Thompson Brown III, 1894-1915., 45 items. PDS. (Box-folder 22:18)
    - A book of sermons copied by Mrs. F[rances] B. Brown, 330 pages, and a separate sermon, 5 June 1890., 15 pages. 2 items. ADrS. (Box-folder 22:19)
      "Given to my son June 5, 1890. Let him read it carefully and may God have mercy on his soul. Amen." (Mrs. Frances B. Brown died in September 1894.)
    Subseries 4: Later Family Members
  - Correspondence and other papers relating to later members of the family: Cary A. Adams (ca. 1900), Judge John Randolph Tucker, 1913-1915, and Capt. David Tucker Brown, 1918-1919. Also includes undated and/or unidentified papers in the collection, 1900-1856, n.d., 85 items. (Box 23:1-30)
    This box contains material related to the Brown and Tucker families after 1900. Accounts of Cary A. Adams are placed at the beginning of the box.
    Newspaper clippings, 1913-1915, from Nome, Alaska, relate to Judge John Randolph Tucker. Another member of the family, Capt. David Tucker Brown, is represented by two letters (1918, 1919) written from France when he was serving as a member of the American Commission to negotiate peace.
    At the end of the box are collected seventeen undated items concerning unidentified persons.
    - Accounts of Cary A. Adams with various merchants, 1900-1907., 15 items. (Box-folder 23:1)
    - Photograph of John Goode, of Bedford County, 1901-1902. (Box-folder 23:2)
      Endorsed: "Pres. of Const. Convention, 1901-2."
    - Sketch of Judge Quarles at the Const. Cony, in Richmond, 1901. (Box-folder 23:3)
    - Appeal to vote for Aaron Graham, Candidate for Congress in Christianburg, Virginia, 6 September 1902. (Box-folder 23:4)
    - Editorial form the Richmond Times-Dispatch, "Our State Income Tax," 1903. (Box-folder 23:5)
    - Advertisements, 1904-1905. (Box-folder 23:6)
    - Announcement of candidacy of J. Taylor Ellyson of Richmond for the position of Lieutenant Governor, 4 March 1905. (Box-folder 23:7)
    - The Book Buyer, a periodical, September 1906., Pages 125-139. PM. (Box-folder 23:8)
    - Newspaper clippings regarding Wm. B. Allison, Theodore Roosevelt, and "The Political Situation, 1876-1908," 1908-1910., 5 items. NCl. (Box-folder 23:9)
    - Advertisement of Dr. Alfred B. Tucker, of Winchester, 7 July [1910]. (Box-folder 23:10)
    - Newspaper clipping concerning Judge John Randolph Tucker taken from newspapers of Nome, Alaska, 1913-1915., 9 items. NCl. (Box-folder 23:11)
      Taken from the Nome Daily Nugget, Nome Democrat and Nome Industrial Worker.
    - Announcement of the Farmer's Winter Institute in Agriculture, 1913-1914, of Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 2 February 1914. (Box-folder 23:12)
    - World Pictures, from The World, New York, 28 November 1915. (Box-folder 23:13)
    - Capt. D[avid] Tucker Brown, Paris, France, to Barbara, 1918-1919., 2 letters. ALS. Covers lacking. (Box-folder 23:14)
      With the "American Commission to Negotiate Peace." There is also mention of John Thompson Brown IV, of Wilmington.
    - Proclamation by Westmoreland Davis, Governor, on "Farm Labor"; song sheet of the Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute, May, August 1918., 2 items. (Box-folder 23:15)
    - Report of Betty Page Cocke, Administratrix of the estate of Lelia B. Cocke, 17 March 1927. (Box-folder 23:16)
    - Miscellaneous clippings and printed matter, 1903-1929., 27 items. (Box-folder 23:17)
    - Sundry of items not related to other papers in the collection, 1700-1856, n.d. (Box-folder 23:18-30)
      - Ship registration certificate, 17[??]. (Box-folder 23:18)
      - Clipping on the death of Jacob Warwick, of Pocahontas City, Virginia, 11 January 1826. (Box-folder 23:19)
      - Revolutionary War service claim, draft on the Bank of Virginia, and article surviving soldier's payments, 24 March 1834., 3 items. PDS. (Box-folder 23:20)
      - Facsimile, "Eupunging Watkins in Senate," 28 March 1834. (Box-folder 23:21)
      - Draft of a letter from John Thomas [to President Jackson], March 1835. (Box-folder 23:22)
        ("From private who served you on the memorable 8th of Jany, 1815.")
      - Contract of William H. Estis, postman of Brooksville, Virginia, 1843, 1851., 2 items. PDS. (Box-folder 23:23)
      - List of payments for service in War of 1812, 7 December 1856. (Box-folder 23:24)
      - [ ] at Philadelphia to Mrs. Brown, n.d. (Box-folder 23:25)
      - Plan for an unidentified monument, n.d. (Box-folder 23:26)
      - Aunt Lelia to Johnny, n.d. (Box-folder 23:27)
      - An invitation to "His Excellency the American Minister" from the Royal Geographical Society, n.d. (Box-folder 23:28)
      - Terrain maps of the Ohio River and the Louisiana Purchase, n.d., 2 items. ADr. (Box-folder 23:29)
      - "Flors's Vocabulary, or the Language of Flowers," n.d. (Box-folder 23:30)
        An alphabetical list of flowers with the characteristics of each expressed symbolically.
    Subseries 5: Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous printed material, including engravings from the nineteenth century, which were included in the collection as received, 1800-?, n.d., ca. 400 items. (Box 24:1-47)